JAMES PERRY

Plainfield, IN • (317) 473-3762 • jpperry74@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Senior Engineer and Software Developer with more than 6 years of experience in project management, strategic planning, and process optimization. Background in establishing standard operating procedures, leading crossfunctional teams, and generating performance reports. Key strengths include data analysis, creative problem solving, and learning new systems.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

C++ Python SQL mySQL NOSQL Aspen ProMV JavaScript GraphQL

EXPERIENCE

2020 – Present Ingredion Incorporated Indianapolis, IN

Senior Engineer 2023 – Present

- Manage small team through task stratification, deliverable organization, and process implementation
- Leverage Lean Six Sigma principles to generate efficiency, execute process improvements, and promote safety
- Serve as Subject Matter Expert (SME) on certain technologies related to company processes and generate
 weekly, monthly, and ad hoc reports as needed with a focus on identifying gaps and mitigating risks
- Lead special projects, including utility relocation/renovation project with an estimated cost of \$3.5MM and a
 utility infrastructure upgrade to implement new technology and materials

Department Manager | Corn Co-Products

2021 - 2022

- Managed team of 15 by designing, implementing, and championing training and talent acquisition programs
- Led more than 10 root cause analysis initiatives across cross-functional teams by identifying action items and liaising with senior leadership, ultimately reducing dryer fire frequency by more than 50%
- Championed programs to increase the autonomy and safety mindset of hourly reports and transitioned the department culture from a fixed mindset to ongoing journey of growth via value-stream mapping

Process Lead | Corn Wet Milling

2020 - 2021

- Coached employees on best practices, standard works, and job expectations while monitoring daily safety, environmental, quality, and OEE and implementing process improvements to address deficiencies
- Led data-driven approach to optimize training that resulted in a 15% improvement in wet corn germ production

2017 - 2020

Archer Daniels Midland Company

Decatur, IL

Process Engineer | Soy Protein Extraction

- Designed and implemented process improvements requiring up to \$1MM in capital while troubleshooting process issues using the DMAIC process to address root causes
- Supervised operators, maintenance, and contractors during major outages and personnel shortages
- Optimized standard operating procedures, PSM documents, and safety requirements while leading the PSM required PHA/HAZOP for the hexane extraction department to create a plan of action and mitigate gaps

EDUCATION AND CERTIFICATIONS

University of Wisconsin

Remote

Coding and Webstack Development Certificate (2023)

Purdue University

West Lafayette, IN

Bachelor of Science, Chemical Engineering (2017)